<I>
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#1:1> <h> 4-18-09</h>
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#2:1> <h> Dear John,</h>

<p> <ICE-USA:W1B-014#3:1>
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#4:1> Well you certainly are right?
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#5:1> Writing certainly is becoming somewhat of a lost art form.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#6:1> Particularly with considering how much time it has taken for me to sit

down and take the time to write you a reply.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#7:1> Please accept, with this reply letter, my sincere apology for the

length & time taken to get this reply letter to you.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#8:1> I like your idea about sending and receiving letters that travel great

distances.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#9:1> It truly is a terrific and amazing thing.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#10:1> And I recall once when we lived on Alma Street you shared some of

your collection of envelopes you've received from 'ver away places.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#11:1> Well, I appreciate your sharing the details of your studies, your

program, and the details involved in the variety of potential choices you'll

have 'llthe near future for career direction and places where you may be

moving to live next.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#12:1> I never realized there was as much involved in the study of education

and ESL.�</p>

<p> <ICE-USA:W1B-014#13:1> After reading about it in your letter it seemed also to make a

lot of sense, that there are requirements to be met and state tests of course

in order to obtain a teaching license for a specialized field such as ESL, as

well as minimum experience requirements pre-licensure.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#14:1> It reminded me somewhat of my own journey in obtaining the MFT

license in California.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#15:1> I'm sure, as you know, t 'mre are education and experience

requirements for the MFT also.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#16:1> Of the total 3,000 hours of experience required, a minimum of 500

must be counseling or psychotherapy with children, families, or couples; for

every 1 hour of personal therapy an MFT intern receives, they can claim 3

hours, up to a total of 300 - - this means you can get credit towards

licensure by being in your own therapy for 100 sessions or about 2 years - -

and you can also count up to 500 hours of training & writing progress notes (

250 each) and there are then some restrictions on certain other kinds of

experience so that people don't become licensed with inadequate experience,

such as an MFT intern can only claim 500 hours from doing group psychotherapy

and only 250 hours doing telephone counseling like working at a crisis line,

so an MFT intern is going to have to do an ample amount of hours doing

one-to-one counseling or therapy.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#17:1> I think this is a very good thing by the way. </p>

<p> <ICE-USA:W1B-014#18:1> One more factor that makes all these experience hours valid is

that every week the MFT intern must meet with a supervisor to discuss their

work and get guidance, one hour of one-to-one supervision is required for

every ten hours doing therapy, or two hours of group supervision for every

ten hours doing therapy.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#19:1> So if an intern has 20 sessions with clients, they'll need two 'llurs

of one-to-one ( individual) supervision or four hours of group! Every week!

Are you confused by this yet?
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#20:1> Finally, all the experience hours and supervision must be obtained

within six years prior to the date the MFT intern submits their application

to sit for the MFT licensing exams.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#21:1> Yes, plural; exams.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#22:1> The first one takes about 4 hours and has 200 multiple choice

questions covering a wide range of topics and critical clinical issues.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#23:1> From what some of my colleagues who have taken ( and passed on their

first try) the exams, the questions can sometimes be kind of tricky.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#24:1> Sometimes the correct answer is fairly obvious, but most of the time

many of the multiple choice answers are probable and correct in most

circumstances and the trick in getting the right one is determining the best

answer or the one that is most correct!
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#25:1> So after the first part is passed, then an MFT intern can take the

second part as soon as they are ready.</p>

<p> <ICE-USA:W1B-014#26:1> This part used to be an excruciating oral exam.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#27:1> Now it 's written and I think the test is one where there are several

clinical vignettes and situations presented and the MFT intern explains all

the aspects and clinical, theoretical, legal and ethical rationale for their

choice of course of action.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#28:1> I would much rather do this in essay or written form than be in a

room with a panel of interviewers to whom I would have to explain myself!
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#29:1> I think it may now be automated by computer, like the first part of

the exam is with 200 multiple choice questions.</p>

<p> <ICE-USA:W1B-014#30:1> Well, as things are now, I have accumulated all the required

hours for every category except the area of child, family or couples

counseling & psychotherapy.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#31:1> In that category I now have 214 more to get 500 ( min), but when I

add all the hours in all the categories, I find a deficit of 245 more.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#32:1> Although this may sound confusing let me explain; overall I'm now 459

hours s 'mrt of the required 3,000 total, and 214 hours short of the required

minimum 500 hours for work with children, families or couples.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#33:1> In other words, I've accumulate 'veo far 2,541 hours.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#34:1> 214 more must be with children, families or couples.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#35:1> The remaining 245 can also be with children, families or couples, or

with one-to-one therapy with adults.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#36:1> Please let me know whether I've thoroughly 'venfused you or whether

all this makes sense!
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#37:1> So now I'm working with chi 'mren at the Family Service Agency of San

Mateo County, in their Child Abuse Treatment or " CHAT" program.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#38:1> I see about 5 or 6 kids each week so it could take another 35 weeks

at this rate to get the remaining 214 that I need, but the program 's grant

expires in September 2009.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#39:1> Another grant is being submitted to extend the program, though it 's

hard to say now whether it will be accepted & approved.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#40:1> Regardless, I'm always asking 'mr more children clients to work with,

and getting some every now & then but the new clients only seem to come in

about equal to the rate of attrition.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#41:1> </p>

<p> <ICE-USA:W1B-014#42:1> You see, in family 's with current or histories of abuse have a

high level of dysfunction and problems are encountered with commitment to

keep regular weekly therapy appointments, let alone problems with family

finance for keeping the telephone working or for transportation.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#43:1> In the meantime I've been hi 've for a position next school year

working at either a middle school or at a high school within Palo Alto

Unified School District doing counseling and psychotherapy with teens onsite.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#44:1> This position should ensure that I get more than enough experience

hours to apply to take the MFT exam sometime next year!
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#45:1> And if the Family Service Agency grant is approved, I can continue

working there concurrently!
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#46:1> It feels great to know this phase will soon be done.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#47:1> With all that said, before I sign off for now, my sister-in-law,

Melissa 's sister Susannah French, has written a children 's novel entitled "

Operation Redwood" using the pen name S. Terrell French and it has just been

published and is being distributed to bookstores and available on Amazon.com!
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#48:1> Look at her website: www.operationredwood.com, and I'm reading it 'm
aloud at night at bedtime to Melissa.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#49:1> Also, she read your letter and wanted to know if you would like a

reply from her as well.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#50:1> I hope this reply comes in time to be helpful to your project,</p>

<h>
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#51:1> All the best to you John, </h> <h>
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#52:1> Kelly, Burlingame, CA </p> <h> 8/20/09</h> <h>
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#53:1> Dear John,</h>

<p> <ICE-USA:W1B-014#54:1> Thanks for your recent letter; we read it over dinner tonight.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#55:1> Sounds like you are starting a big adventure - - I hope you are happy

in your new position & that you have a great group of kids to work with &

some interesting colleagues with whom to work.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#56:1> I don't really know the area where you are living, but my sister

lived in Cambridge when she was at Harvard & I can tell you that does seem

like a dynamic, happening place to live.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#57:1> When she was there Tracey Chapman was a street musician & ice cream

stores/shops had this tasty treat: " mix ins" where they would mix in your

favorite cookie/candy into the ice cream of your choice yummy & memorable.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#58:1> When my sister was in Cambridge, I was at school at Earlham College a

tiny school in the very small rural town of Richmond, Indiana.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#59:1> We had fun with the city mouse/country mouse school visits.</p>

<p> <ICE-USA:W1B-014#60:1> By the way we've been 'veing fun helping her tour & promote her

book - - Operation Redwood.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#61:1> If I remember correctly, you were able to join us for her book

reading/signing here in Burlingame.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#62:1> It 's fun to read local positive reviews.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#63:1> Kelly is also in a point of transition, but I should let him describe

this more - - I'm continui 'm working full time as a midwife doing ( symbol

for female) health care, prenatal care and delivering babies.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#64:1> It is a very fulfilling & rewarding job with lots of responsibility &

some crazy hours.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#65:1> I've been 'veere ~ 7 yrs now & occasionally I think about looking for

a new job ( some of my classmates working in the Bay Area are working fewer

hrs for more money), but in many ways I love this job - - the patients are

great, I feel very supported in my work & I like the continuity in the womens

lives I serve & I really feel I can be myself in my work place.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#66:1> I know this is not always true & I don't take it for granted.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#67:1> I don't know if things will change when Kelly finally gets his hours

and passes his MFT exams - - this is aways in the future - - so in the famous

words of my mother - - " we'll s 'll... Kelly & I have had the good fortune to

take a lot of vacations this summer. </p>

<p> <ICE-USA:W1B-014#68:1> First, we took 10 days off in early July.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#69:1> We started in Ashland where we stayed for 3 nights in a great youth

hostel very near the Shakespeare festival.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#70:1> We saw the world premier of a new production of Dan Quixote which was

interesting.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#71:1> Then we had a great next day - - leisurely breakfast, white water

rafting, visit to a local winery where we stayed for an open air blue grass

concert.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#72:1> Very relaxed & spontaneous day! The next day we had the 4th of July

activities, a long nap, and an amazing production of MacBeth.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#73:1> Then we bid a fond farwell to Ashland Cove ( one of our honeymoon

towns) & headed up to Bend in the high dessert.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#74:1> We enjoyed a couple of days there dining atop Mt. Bachelor exploring

sleeping volcanic mountain snow topped peaks.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#75:1> When we finally had to leave, there were many sites left to be seen -

- lava tubes, high mountain desert museums.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#76:1> We do hope to return to that beautiful area.</p>

<p> <ICE-USA:W1B-014#77:1> The whole population seemed incredibly fit & there were a bunch

of geezers biking up totally high mountains.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#78:1> After a number of days in central Oregon we headed through the great

little town of Sislers to the coast of Oregon to a quaint little town called 'Seaside.'

Whereas the central Oregon area was very hot in the upper 90s - - the coast

was foggy & chilly as we've gro 'veaccustomed to.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#79:1> After several days, we drove up to fort Clotsop to see where Lewis &

Clark & their party made a U turn, if you will.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#80:1> Then we turned in-land & headed to Portland where we would spend a

long festive friendly weekend with 3 of my college buddies along with some

husbands & kids.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#81:1> Again we were staying in a fantastic hostel in downtown Portland & we

walked everywhere the entire time we were there except for our jaunt to the

waterfalls & the Gorge.</p>

<p> <ICE-USA:W1B-014#82:1> I guess you've see 'veome of the photos on Kelly 's facebook &

these are some of the stories behind the pictures.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#83:1> A little while after I got back I hopped on a plane for a long

weekend to surprise my Dad for his 70th birthday - - my sister & her ids were

there already so my surprised & delighted papa was happy to have all his

chickadees with him.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#84:1> Then in early August, Kelly & I took my mother, step father,

Susannah, her husband & her kids up to the mountains above Fresno.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#85:1> The area is called Harington Lake & it 's in the Sierras approx mid

way between Yosemite & Kings Canyon.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#86:1> We stayed in a luxurious cabin & sailed & swam in the lake; explored

the rocky creak called Dinky creek; & Kelly & the kids jumped 20 feet from

large boulders into chilly mountain streams.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#87:1> We found a local bakery that made the cinnamon rolls Kelly remembers

from his childhood.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#88:1> Several nights in a row we lay outside in the chilly mountain air &

counted shooting stars.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#89:1> We saw ~ 100!!</p>

<p> <ICE-USA:W1B-014#90:1> What an amazing week introducing the family to this favorite area

of the country from Kelly 's past.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#91:1> Things are getting back into the Fall groove - - we may enjoy some

more of summers' bounty ( tomatoes, corn, peaches, etc...) before changing to

Fall apples.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#92:1> Also - - you may be interested to know - - we have plans to see 4

baseball games in September - - 2 Giants games & 2 Oakland games.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#93:1> Glad to hear your Angels are well & playing good baseball.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#94:1> I guess we're 'reping there 's a chance the Giants could get the

wildcard & be in the playoffs.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#95:1> That would be fun! Well, I' 'llsign off for now, so there 's something

for Kelly to write about.
<ICE-USA:W1B-014#96:1> Good luck with your new undertakings - - I hope this is a wonderful

experience for you.</p> <h> Our very best,</h> <h> Melissa</h> </I>